today we're going to move into a
transition from the Middle Ages or the
medieval period to the beginning of the
modern age in the history of philosophy
and I don't want to leave you with the
impression the no significant
philosophical thought was done between
Saint Thomas Aquinas and Renee Descartes
for example in the 17th century
there were many very important
philosophers who stepped to the plate
during the that period Bonaventure done
scotus Occam for example avalor another
and but
what happens
later on in Western history is so
significant for the shaping of modern
philosophy that I would like to spend
the time on those things not everyone
was simply falling dead at the feet of
Saint Thomas Aquinas there were still
some original thinking going on but
Thomas did dominate the Middle Ages
and so we're going to move beyond that
to the Renaissance that began in the
13th century at least in the western
world as I've already mentioned there
was already a Renaissance going on in
the Muslim world where attempts have
been made by the Islamic philosophers to
create a synthesis between Muslim
Theology and Aristotelian thought
but when we talk about the Renaissance
in the Western World we're talking about
that movement that began in Florence in
Italy in the 13th century and made
significant strides forward in the 14th
century
initially
the Renaissance which means rebirth
was a Reawakening to ancient culture and
thought a rediscovery of the ancient
poets and dramatists and particularly
the ancient philosophers
and there was a renewed interest both in
the ancient Romans particularly Cicero
and the ancient Greeks the rediscovery
of Plato and Aristotle and so on
now in the 14th century
Cosimo the Medici and you've heard of
the the medicis the very fabulously
wealthy Italian family
ruled more or less as king of Florence
and Cosimo de Medici founded the new
platonic Republic now he himself
represents something of a transitional
figure because in the 13th century much
of the impetus for The Rebirth of
ancient culture was directed not only
out of an interest in antiquity
but also there was a growing climate of
turning the attention of the people away
from the major concerns of the church
which tended to fix people's attention
on Heavenly things
to a new concern for Humanity and for
life here and now so the earlier
thinkers in the Renaissance in the 13th
century were either indifferent towards
the the church into the Christian faith
but we're positively hostile towards
them but in the 14th century with the
the Medici family's love of antiquity
there was still a commitment to the
church and there was an attempt to marry
some of these discoveries uh from and to
rediscoveries from Antiquity to the
contemporary church situation and you
know the Medici family was a family that
was intimately involved with the Roman
Catholic Church of that time
for example
Cosimo's great-grandson
was perhaps the most
feigned of the medicis his name was
Lorenzo the Magnificent and the
Magnificent and Lorenzo the Magnificent
was the one who first took Michelangelo
under his wing and he even invited him
into his home where he lived with the
family and so on
until the
early death of Lorenzo the Magnificent
one of Lorenzo's Sons
became Pope Alexander VI and I'll talk
about that more later
but in any case the basic impetus of the
Renaissance at first seemed to work
against classical Christianity but then
after a Time began to work as a support
system to Historic Christianity the
motto of the Renaissance was the phrase
ad Fontes
to the sources to the sources and that
or to the Fountain if you will the word
font means fountain or source
and so
what that meant was go back to the to
the earliest sources of Western
Civilization recover the thinking of
Aristotle Plato and so on and so a new
effort was made to learn the Greek
language and the Latin language
and in addition to that however came the
Christian humanists of whom Erasmus of
Rotterdam was the most famous who lived
in the 16th century
and in their effort to recover the
greatness of antiquity one of the
sources that they were concerned about
studying afresh
was the scripture particularly the New
Testament
and so there was a whole new Accent on
mastering the biblical languages which
brought in its wake a new investigation
of the original sources of Christian
thought
and at first that was somewhat tame but
after a while there were those who saw a
radical dichotomy between what they were
reading in the original sources of
scripture and what had developed
historically in the institutional Church
that was based more on tradition than on
the original sources so
the first challenge really that came to
the medieval synthesis or what we call
the classical synthesis was the
challenge brought by the Renaissance in
this where the initial
movements that were going sooner or
later to displace The Originals or the
the medieval structure of the University
where it was commonplace to think in the
University that the queen of all of The
Sciences was theology
and philosophy was called her handmaiden
so that the theological faculty would be
the dominant faculty of the entire
University and then second perhaps in
command was the department of philosophy
well as you know today that's not the
way it is and some radical changes were
already starting to take place as a
result of the impetus of the Renaissance
also at this time
as part of the Renaissance mindset was a
challenge
to teleology
I remember when I was a senior in
college
I still had not yet taken my required
course in freshman biology the reason
for that was scheduling when I was a
freshman I took Greek and the only time
I could take Greek conflicted when the
courses were offered for what they
called bonehead biology biology 101.
and so I didn't take it until I was a
senior I'd been a philosophy major and
all of that sort of thing and I remember
the first day in class the biology
professor said something that Disturbed
me greatly
and her opening lecture she said you
must learn
if you're going to be scientific
and to engage in the pursuit of the
knowledge of living things as we're
doing in biology is that you have to set
aside any concerns of teleology
and I you know I said wait a minute
that's like telling me I can never ask
the question what is the purpose
of these things that we're studying
and I had real problems with that
philosophical problems and Theological
problems what I didn't realize was that
she was merely reflecting
an attitude towards science that had
been deeply rooted already in the
Renaissance
the Renaissance reacted against the
medieval educations
[Music]
fixation they believed on trying to
interpret everything that we learn in
this world according to how it fit with
the divine plan and the Divine Purpose
you think God was banished from the
school room only in in the 20th century
but this challenge was that we are to
study things for their own sake and not
to be concerned about how they fit in
with the ultimate purposes of God and so
on this was a serious challenge to
Christian thinking because the Christian
worldview was such that wanted to
understand everything that we learn in
light of its relationship to the
purposes of God now a second major
challenge
two the medieval realm was the
Scientific Revolution
that came in the 15th and 16th century
particularly as you've all heard the
copernican revolution
where the astronomer Copernicus
wrote a a a a a theory
that attacked the traditional theory of
the ptolemaic view of the universe where
the ancient Ptolemy taught in the
Aristotelian tradition
that the Earth is the center of the
universe in the center of our solar
system that was called Geo
centricity
and over against geocentricity Geo's the
Greek word from we get from gase which
means earth the earth is the center of
the solar system
Copernicus arguing from mathematics and
so on argued for heliocentricity
well he did this basically on the
research of Kepler and others uh and and
the mathematical considerations to save
the phenomenon phenomena as Plato had
had urged and he just said that the
whole Paradigm of look considering the
Sun as being the center of the solar
system rather than the earth just made a
whole lot more sense well this created a
major controversy in the 16th century
over
the authority of the church
the authority of the church was being
challenged because the church had
embraced the ptolemaic view of the
universe believing that the Bible taught
that the Earth was the center of the
universe
we know the famous Galileo episode where
Galileo was condemned when the Bishops
of the church refused to even look
through his telescope to see if there
would be corroborative confirming
evidence of heliocentricity if you read
the writings of Luther and Calvin on the
Protestant side both Luther and Calvin
vehemently
castigated the thinking of Copernicus
just about everybody in the church
Protestant Catholic alike at that time
saw a significant challenge to Historic
Christianity by the new science now the
new science came
uh
being born on the wings of two important
developments one was a new scientific
method the scientific method that you
learned when you went to grade school
the scientific method that is based upon
two elements the element of induction
and the element of deduction
induction is when you gather data when
you collect samples when you conduct
experiments and then deduction has to do
with the reasoning from the data that
you have collected
and so the scientific method was not
satisfied with discovering truth simply
by philosophical reflection or by
theological Dogma but rather they wanted
to look at the facts they wanted to
examine the Earth as it is discoverable
to whatever level it is and so on
but in addition to this method
and we also add that in the deduction
side math and mathematicians
were growing in importance in this
period as we will see
but in addition to this there was an
explosion of Technology there was a real
technological Revolution that took place
at this time
and it was an explosion of Technology of
instruments particularly instruments of
measurement
the development of the microscope
the development of the telescope two
very important historical discoveries
because now our ability to see and
perceive the external world was enhanced
by a virtual Quantum Leap
where the telescope means to look across
or look far
and greatly enhance our ability to see
into the far distances of the heavens
in addition that which was Tiny so small
that could not be perceived by the naked
eye was now suddenly opened to our Vista
by virtue of the microscope
and people were discovering
microorganisms and molecules and
bacteria and all that sort of thing
which just radically revolutionized the
entire scientific
world now in addition to the changes and
advances in science one of the things
that was
came in its wake was the age of
exploration
and this was enhanced by these new
instruments
this was the period of vast
worldwide exploration by Vasco da Gama
and Magellan and Christopher Columbus in
the 15th century and so on in fact
Columbus's discovery of America was a
discovery of a new world
which changed the whole dynamic of
of Commerce
of business
and the like in this time and so on the
heels of these things came a new
economic system
that is as the scientific changes were
taking place there were also changes in
business and commerce and as the changes
came in business and commerce came
changes in economics in fact the
probably the most significant single
change in the realm of Economics was
with the use of money
now there's always been money they've
always had I mean there's been some
medium of exchange but still the guilds
and the economic system of the Middle
Ages functioned basically basically on
the basis of exchange of goods and
services
where money was not conceived of as a
commodity
but with the birth of what we call
capitalism
everything changed
because now money
was seen as something that had inherent
value and could grow and make a person
Wealthy by investment
and one of the
um
most favorable Investments that came
about at this time
was the investment in Exploration
Ventures
remember you read in when you were in
junior high school about Columbus trying
desperately to get finances to test his
theories of finding a shorter way to the
East Indies for commercial reasons and
he goes to Ferdinand and Isabella and
tries to get somebody to finance his
expedition and in those days the wealthy
people who had acquired a lot of money
or Capital were looking for ways to
invest it and one of the things that
they did would be to invest in
Exploration Ventures just like people do
today with drilling for gasoline or oil
or whatever
and the way it went was this if the
investor gave Christopher Columbus
X number of dollars to finance his
exploratory voyage
any Goods that were brought back
75 percent of them went to the investor
and the other 25 percent to the
adventurer
who had to share those profits with by
paying wages to his Sailors and so on
but then the Sailor would now have
Capital that he could reinvest in
further Explorations and so this is the
way the thing went now part again of
what came in the new economics was a
moral crisis
and an ecclesiastical crisis with
respect
to interest
the Bible historically condemns usury
which in its most naked form involves
the charging of interest for loans
and throughout the Middle Ages all
interest was disallowed
but because the whole new system
required borrowing and financing
interest now became allowable as long as
it wasn't
too exploitive and the Very word usury
became redefined both in the commercial
world and in the church it's interesting
for us when we read Luther in the 16th
century how much tension he's given to
the ethical question of usury
but usury now became ex defined as
excessive interest rather than the use
of interest at all so this is another
vast change that was coming to pass in
the world
now in addition in addition to this
we also encounter in the 16th century
the greatest upheaval of the classical
synthesis that took place at all and
that was the impact of the Protestant
Reformation
and there were all kinds of reasons for
that not just theological but there were
issues of a rising sense of nationalism
and great resentment that had been
accumulating over the centuries against
Roman rule because the church was
powerful not only ecclesiastically but
militarily and politically the pope was
the most powerful political person in
the world during the Middle Ages
and so there were countries such as
Germany and others that were sick and
tired of what they called ultramontanism
being ruled from over the mountains
and there was this yearning for National
Independence
in addition to this there was the moral
decay of the church which the humanists
the Christian humanists even Erasmus was
caught were calling for radical reforms
it focused principally on the behavior
of priests and chiefly the behavior of
certain Medieval popes the two great
sins as it were or points of corruption
that had infected the Church of this
time were the sins of simony
and nepotism
simony in is when it gets its name from
the New Testament book of Acts when
Simon Magus you know Simon the Magician
tried to buy the power of the Holy
Spirit from Peter and Peter said may
your money perish with you and so simony
came to describe that practice by which
the church sold Church offices because
they were lucrative
so people were buying The Bishop's hat
or the Cardinal hat whether they had any
moral or spiritual integrity at all if
they had the money they could become
Bishops or Cardinals there were several
occasions in there where we had teenage
Cardinals and at least two teenage popes
because even the papacy was being
purchased by Rich and Powerful families
like The Borgias and the medicis and
this is a matter of record and and the
Roman Catholic church today acknowledges
this because they've since reformed the
process but at the time the church was
in great moral corruption
nepotism was the granting of church
offices not simply by virtue of payment
but to keep it in the family I always
say nepotism is all right as long as you
keep it in the family but they uh you
were getting nephews and nieces sons and
daughters and putting them in strategic
places of uh of ecclesiastical power so
this brought forth a great Grassroots
reaction
and even a reaction in the church in the
15th century the church attempted
conciliarism whereby the church voted
that church councils would be the
supreme authority and even the pope
would have to obey the decisions of the
council was like the Magna Carta of the
church whereby Kings would have to pay
attention to a constitution
or a parliament
unfortunately the Pope's had rejected it
and it failed at that time and so as we
move into the 16th century the
corruption is at perhaps its worst stage
with the so-called worldly popes of that
era now these are just some of the
currents and then some of the winds that
were blowing at that time that prepared
the world of theoretical thought for the
Modern Age which we're going to look at
in terms of the work of Renee Descartes